You don't know what God is making while
you're aching.
you're crying. You don't know what God
is making while you're lonely. You don't
know what God is making while you're
suffering, but I declare unto you he is
making something. You can't always see
what the master is doing. Only when we
look back, then we see that God had a
plan
when all we had was pain.
You know the funniest thing to me is
that poor people think that rich people
don't get crushed.
They think that if they had money,
they'd have everything.
But crushing is the one thing in the
world that you can count on to be
totally unbiased.
It is not one bit prejudice.
If you're white, you get crushed.
If you're black, you get crushed. If
you're young, you get crushed. If you're
old, you get crushed. If you're female,
you get crushed. If you're male, you get
crushed. If you make a lot of money, you
get crushed. If you can't find a job,
you get crushed. Crushing is not
prejudice. It comes to every person's
life. We all experience seasons of death
and desperation.
Dreams dashed.
Relationships crumble.
Businesses fall.
And it seems like you're going to die.
Whether that business is a big corporate
office
bringing in billions of dollars,
reporting to a shareholders,
or whether it's a mom and pop shop,
a dry cleaning service or a cupcake
shop, you go through changes.
It is the crushing that gives you
wisdom.
You cannot buy wisdom in a store. You
cannot get it in a jar. It is the
crushing that gives you wisdom.
It is Nelson Mandela
wrongfully in prison
shut up in a prison in the middle of an
island for years
never knowing that while he was an
inmate having food shoved to him like a
dog to eat off the ground that he would
be the president of South Africa.
And if he had not endured the prison, he
wouldn't make the presidency.
It is the prison that created the
presidency. That is what crushing is.
It is the ability to endure the wisdom
of the vintner
for the vintner knows exactly where to
crush you.
I know Nelson Mandela would not have
picked such an unsavory place to be
president.
Most presidents don't go to jail to be
They go to Yale to be president.
But not Nelson. Nelson went to jail and
he still got there. You must believe
that in spite of the suffering you will
still get there.
That God has a watch and it never loses
time. And he knows exactly when to raise
you and exactly when to bring you out.
And when the stage is set and the time
is right, nobody can hold you down when
God gets ready to raise you up.
But the problem with the seed is that it
can't think.
So it doesn't understand the suffering
and it doesn't understand the pain and
it can't hear me. And sometimes the
hardest part about being a preacher is
that you want so much for the people to
get it and sometimes the people who
needed the most, they really don't
really hear you.
That you're on course when you're off
course.
That you're planted when you thought you
were buried.
That the only way up to go down.
That everything in the kingdom is
backwards.
That if you exalt yourself, he'll abase
you.
If you abase yourself, he'll exalt you.
Death is necessary to create life.
Jesus says, "I come that you might have
life." And then dies.
Because the cost of life was death.
Do you understand the words that are
coming out of my mouth?
That right now, those of you that are
watching and those of you that are
listening at me maybe going through
something that seems unbearable and
painful and personal and difficult to
articulate to anybody else because pain
is always personal. How wrong. It's not
right. It's not right. It wasn't right
for my daughter to be pregnant.
I'm a bishop seen all over the country.
It's not right for us to have a private
moment in a public place. It's not right
that my mother who was the smartest
person I have ever seen in my life would
gradually have her mind peeled back like
an onion until she couldn't tell a
banana from an orange. It's not right.
Sometimes it is necessary in order to
cultivate in the vineyard, you have to
disrupt the soil. You have to turn it
over. You have to disrupt everything
around it. You have to pull some weeds
sometimes. You got to uproot some
plants. You have to cause dishevel in
order to get where you want to go. And
it's messy and it's dirty and it's not
right.
But it's necessary.
And we feel pain. And sometimes there's
pain we don't even have anybody to talk
to about.
Private secret pain. Pain locked up
behind your lips. Pain behind your
makeup. Pain behind your nice clothes.
Sometimes you dress up to hide so nobody
can see how deep down inside you're
hurting. Intimacy is into me see.
And yet nobody sees into me.
And so I paint this face of who you
think I am and smile the way you want me
to smile and I perform for you and
that's the only reason I get tired of
you.
Because I yearn to take the mask off and
be who I really am and say I am confused
and I am hurting and I am suffering and
this crushing feels like death. The
death of my ideas is a birthing place of
his purpose.
God works
in crushing.
And it pleased him to bruise him.
It pleased God
to bruise us.
Not because he is sadistic.
Not because we are masochistic.
It pleases him to bruise us because he
knows that the end result will put us in
a state
where we can no longer ferment.
Where we can handle a setback, a
disappointment, where we can handle a
hurt.
See, wine doesn't spoil. It'll last for
years and years and years in the dark,
in the basement, in the cellar because
it's been through enough crushing to
endure time.
And you can tell when a person has been
crushed because they are survivors.
People who have been crushed are
survivors.
When my church emptied out and we were
going through COVID and I had to preach
in an empty by myself, it was no problem
because I started preaching in an empty
building and I don't need people in
order to do what God called me to do. I
don't need applause, I don't need
clapping, I don't need shouting, I don't
need dancing, I don't need an organ. All
I need is what's in me.
If God is inside of you, all crushing
will do is push him out.
And might had this final remark, If
Satan was smart, he would never push.
Because if you never pushed me, I
wouldn't secrete the glory.
If you never pushed me, I would have
never found out who I was. If you never
pushed me, I would have never found out
what I could do. If you never pushed me,
I would have never found out what I
could be.
But the more we are afflicted, the Bible
says, the more we grow.
So, if you feel like you're being
afflicted, and if you feel like you're
dying, and if you feel like he's pushing
on you, hang in there.
The best is yet to come.
Now unto him that is able to do
exceedingly abundantly above all that we
may ask or think, according to the power
that works in us.
Simply means that the seed doesn't know
what it's becoming.
If he's able to do exceedingly
abundantly above all that we may ask or
think,
that means we have no idea what he's
making when he's making us.
And the seed doesn't know
what the bit mirror is doing.
He just has to trust him.
Constricted to his methods.
Imprisoned by his purpose.
Locked up in a situation where you just
have to trust him.
I didn't wake up the person you see
today.
Not by a long shot.
Nowhere close. If you would have met me
at 18 and told me that I would end up
being this, I would have laughed in your
face.
If you'd have told me at 16 that I would
end up here, all of my neighbors would
have laughed in your My classmates would
have laughed in your face.
I was a wretched little boy.
But I didn't know what God was making.
I thought I was going to be a musician,
but I didn't know what God was making.
But little by little, step by step, day
by day, situation by situation, he was
leading me into my purpose and destiny.
Not only by the doors that open,
but by the doors that close.
From humble beginnings.
I I mean, we were we were po'.
Po' is when you cannot afford the oar.
My idea of rich people were people who
who had grass in their yards.
Rich people were people who had air
conditioning. And a doorbell meant you
were wealthy.
Just a doorbell. I couldn't imagine
having a doorbell with the chimes that
rang and the little things that hung
down. It was amazing. I saw it on TV.
What I had was a raggedy screen door
that was cut down at the bottom and a
sunken porch where the concrete had
rotted out of the middle of it and I had
to step over to come into the house.
And if you didn't fasten the screen
door, it'd swing open.
And that's where I came from.
But I didn't know what God was making.
And it was necessary that I come from
there
because of the heights he would take me
to.
I would never have to question in myself
why I do what I do.
Because I did it broke.
And I did it lonely, and I did it with
no money, and I did it with no car, and
I did it with my lights off, and I did
it in the crushing.
So that now, as he begins to bring me
into my senior years,
I can see God doing things with me that
I never imagined possible.
That I would be sitting across from
Oprah Winfrey on her show
was something I never asked for.
That I would sit down with the CEO of
AT&T, then Randall Stephenson,
and have a discussion
about equity is something that I
couldn't imagine. AT&T?
That I would be closing on property
right next to Tyler Perry Studios?
That it it's got grass.
I mean, it's got really grass.
That that I would write books that were
translated into multiple languages
around the world. Woman that are losing
has been translated into 12 different
languages.
They say they say it's Japanese. I can't
read it, but it I'll trust that that's
what it is. It is Mandarin and and and
in Chinese. I can't read it, but I trust
that that's what it is. That that would
come out of a guy who was just writing
short stories in the eighth grade.
I can't understand it. You don't know
what God is making while you're aching.
You don't know what God is making while
you're aching.
you're crying. You don't know what God
is making while you're lonely. You don't
know what God is making while you're
suffering. But I declare unto you he is
making something.
You may feel dislocated. You may feel
dislodged. You can't always see what the
master is doing. Only when we look back,
then we see that God had a plan
when all we had was pain.
God had a plan. I had no idea that my
daughter getting pregnant. I hated it. I
it hurt. It It's not about
embarrassment. It wasn't about image. It
It was just my baby girl.
It was about her future, about her
destiny.
And I thought this is a mistake. This is
wrong. This is wrong. This can't happen.
This can't happen to us.
And now when she stands up in the pulpit
and preach I realized that if she hadn't
have gotten pregnant, she wouldn't have
been the person that she became and that
going backwards is what drove her
forward and that God was smarter than I
was and he knows exactly what to take to
bring you to the place that he can get
out of you what he wants out of you and
he doesn't care whether you're
embarrassed or not and he doesn't care
whether people talk about you or not. He
doesn't care what they think about you.
He only cares that he gets out of you
what he put inside of you.
He will take you from seed to bearing
fruit.
And you don't get to choose the method
he uses.
You don't get to pick the tool that he
cuts you with.
It may have been your first
relationship.
It may have been a rape.
It may have been childhood abuse.
But it shaped something in you.
As horrific as it was.
That made you self-reliant and able to
stand.
And when you got through crying about
it, you woke up a tougher woman than you
were a girl.
Does anybody know what I'm talking
about?
The thing I love the most about him
is that God never gives up on you.
He doesn't wait till you're in the bad
place and then walk out like people do.
Because people are great when you're up.
But when you're down, they'll run out.
When you're weak, they'll run out. When
you make mistakes, they'll run out. And
the church is masterful,
masterful
at killing its wounded.
It's masterful at that. We have no real
method to really restore our wounded,
especially when they're talented.
So we shoot them for being too much like
us.
And there is no place to recover.
But just because man is through with
you, does not mean that God is through
with you. And I don't know who I'm
talking to today, but I feel like I'm
talking to somebody. Just because man
has turned his back and found out
something about you and said you're
nobody, doesn't mean that God is through
with you because whatever they found
out, God already knew.
You have never surprised God. You have
never shocked God. You have never left
God scratching his head. So, stop being
frustrated
because he never
ever
gives up on you. And that
is crushing.
The uniqueness of being a human is the
senses that God has equipped us with
to be able to be in touch with the
world.
I know I am alive because I see, I
smell, I touch, I feel my senses.
And the very thing that he equipped me
with that is unique, that makes me able
to survive even in the jungle of life,
is also the thing that gives me
discomfort
when my situation changes.
And we talked about dirty places.
And we've talked about disruptive
places. And we've talked about
discomfort, but we have not talked about
smelly places.
I want to talk about the discomfort of
dung.
The things that God uses to fertilize
you
smell.
And they smell bad.
The rubbish, the refuse, the dung
is what the vine dresser uses
to make mulch.
It's what he puts all around you when he
really wants you to grow
tall and strong and fruitful.
He puts stink
all around you.
And you can't buy enough cologne to
cover it up.
Because when it stinks,
it stinks.
A marriage that stinks
stinks.
A bad relationship with your child
It stinks in public. It stinks with the
principal. It stinks in school. It
stinks in prison. It stinks in jail. It
stinks in court. It stinks.
God uses stinky stuff.
You must realize that God uses those
things
so that we will become
what he has created for us to be.
That out of that, the nutrients that are
necessary
come from the stink we've been in.
And if you can endure through your
senses the discomfort of the aroma,
eventually God is going to get something
fragrant out of the funk you've been in.
That fragrance would come from funk.
It's hard to explain, but it's true.
It is true nonetheless that some kind of
way that stability would come out of
being stuck.
Stuck.
I love the commercial where the woman
falls down on the grass. She's an old
lady and she says, "Help!
I've fallen
and I can't get up."
Because somebody watching me right now,
you've fallen
and you can't get up.
But if you holler help,
God will get some glory
out of the funk you're in.
The pain you're in, the disgrace you're
in, the discomfort you're in,
the crisis you're in, the turmoil you're
in,
you will rise again.
In the words of Maya Angelou, and still
I rise.
Look back over your life and how many
things tried to crush you,
and still I rise.
We don't clap for ourselves.
We are so busy complaining about where
we have not gotten to that we don't
acknowledge where we have come from.
And every now and then you need to throw
yourself a party and put a hat on your
head and blow a whistle and bake
yourself a cake and put some candles on
it and light it and celebrate the fact
that you have survived
the funk.